Phillip: What are the differences between
an ineffective team and an effective team?
Ineffective teams are usually made up of
people who don’t really work well together.
Maddy: Individuals within the team
may show favouritism, put their own
goals ahead of team goals, and deflect
responsibility for their own mistakes.
Some members may not even have
the appropriate skills or too many
members may have the same skills.
Ineffective teams may also take actions
before issues are examined or resolved,
leading to unconstructive disagreements
and members feeling vulnerable.
Phillip: Effective teams on the other
hand are made up of people who have
complimentary skills and can work together
to accomplish the goals of the team.
So, let’s have a look at behaviours that might
be seen in effective teams in more detail.
Maddy: Safe to be vulnerable
In an effective team, no one feels
like they need to keep their guard up.
That’s because they know that everyone is on
the same side, working towards the same goals.
They know their team will support them,
encourage them, and help them grow and achieve.
They also know they’re safe to express
ideas without the fear of ridicule.
For example, a new team member proposes an
idea around tackling a difficult part of the
current project, but they don’t realise this
has been tried before and found not to work.
The team won’t criticise or mock them
for suggesting it, instead it’s used
as a learning opportunity to explain
why it didn’t work, and time is taken
to thank them for their contribution.
Phillip: Ego-free zone
In an effective team, people aren’t out
for themselves, they’re there for the team.
Although individual ambition should be encouraged,
in an effective team a person’s ambitions
are caught up in the success of their team.
They put their team first and invest their energy
and talent into achieving the team’s goals.
Maddy: Constructive disagreements
Team members will always have disagreements,
but in an effective team, these should
be about finding the right solution, and
not about people just pushing their own
agenda or opinion, for the sake of it.
Disagreements and debates are
respectful and polite, and personal
feelings are kept to one side.
The target is always about finding the best
solution to allow the team to hit their goals.
For example, during a tense part of a project,
there are different possible pathways through.
During a discussion about this, two team
members in particular, have differing, but
very passionate ideas about what will work.
Although they’re forthright with one another,
they still give each other time to fully explain
their proposed idea so the team can decide.
And, when an option is selected, the
person whose idea wasn’t used is thanked
for their contribution to the discussion,
and they respect the team’s decision.
Phillip: Accountability
In an effective team, people take
responsibility for their actions.
They don’t try and deflect or blame
others if things go wrong, instead
they acknowledge their mistakes openly.
This is why ‘safe to be vulnerable’ is important.
When a mistake happens, it’s safe to take
ownership of it because everyone’s main concern
is making things better, not handing out blame.
Accountability also allows people to feel pride
in their work when things go right, as long
as they recognise the role of the team too.
Maddy: Trust
Members of an effective team trust one another.
They know that everyone is there for the same
reason and that everyone wants to work together.
By showing one another trust,
the team will show you trust too.
Phillip: Honesty and integrity
An effective team is one where people
hold themselves to the same standards
that they hold their peers to.
They’re honest about themselves, what they’re
worried about and what they’re proud of.
They don’t apply double standards or favouritism.
They respect everyone’s achievements
and help everyone through their trials.
So, you can see effective teams create bonds
and strong relationships between members, and
understand the goals and targets expected of them.
They work as a team, for the team
to achieve their defined team goals,
and not as individuals with agendas.